hey what's going on guys it's justin at
saltstrung and in this video we're going
to take a closer look at the daiwa
totula svtw there is a lot to talk about
in this video there's a lot of pros and
features packed into this reel we're
also going to address a few cons that i
think you guys really need to consider
before buying this reel if you're
interested and we're going to ask the
question which is when might you want to
use a bait caster for insure salt water
fishing before we dive into the specs of
this tetula svtw i do want to point out
there is another newer model that daiwa
made of the tetula svtw uh it is
virtually the same reel
in concept it's a little bit smaller
compact body it's got a shorter handle
it's got a zero adjust spool tension
knob
but
for us as inshore anglers i like the
fact that diawa kept this is what i'm
going to show here on the specs
they kept their two crbb or their
corrosion resistant ball bearings in
this series of their tethula svtw and as
an insure angler i think any opportunity
you have to have increased performance
or increase the length of
like new performance on your products
you'll take it wherever you can get it
so they have two crbbs included in their
spool and at the side plate around their
magforce brake design which we're going
to dive into a little bit later in the
review but looking at some more of the
specs the tetula svtw actually comes in
three different speed models they have a
six three to one seven three to one and
eight three to one gear ratio uh their
hyper speed is really fast but the seven
point three to 1 i think offers a good
balance of speed and power in the reel
so we decided to go with their middle
option
again 29 and a half inches per turn for
pickup is fantastic for a baitcaster
that is a lot of line retrieve back now
it's really tough to say you know it's
really hard to compare apples to oranges
in terms of the line pickup of a bait
caster to a spinning setup i know some
spinning reels can pick up 34 35 inches
per turn but for a baitcaster that is a
great rate of speed for pickup
and in terms of weight we're looking at
7.2 ounces on this tetula and 13.2
pounds of drag again apples to oranges
there's some spinning setups that can
put out way more drag pressure but just
in the sheer design of a baitcaster and
how line comes on and off the spool
you're going to have the most control
and torque over a fish because line's
going to come directly off of a spool as
opposed to at a 90 degree angle on a
spinning setup so i think you're going
to get the most out of this especially
when you're fishing close around
structure so the first major feature
that i want to talk about on this reel
is what daiwa calls their sv concept now
guys if you're anything like me
i am not much of a baitcast user and the
number one reason and i'm sure a lot of
people will agree is that baitcasters
can be frustrating because of backlash
that is arguably the most frustrating
thing on a baitcaster baitcasters
perform very differently than spinning
setups but they also have a lot more
variables to consider that when you dial
it in just right can be to your
advantage they have tension adjustments
on the spool they have brakes even the
line that you use on the bait caster
whether it's braided line or it's
fluorocarbon the weight of the braid can
affect the tension on the spool when
it's spinning so i think inherently
that's why a lot of guys have been
apprehensive to consider baitcasters
especially the guys fishing inshore but
i will say that daiwa's sv concept helps
eliminate a lot of things and a lot of
frustrations that i think any fishermen
whether it's freshwater water doesn't
matter would have with a baitcaster as a
whole and that's what the sv concept is
sv stands for
stress-free ie
no backlash which we're going to show
here in a video clip in a minute and the
v stands for versatile
which means that the design and the
weight of the spool and how it interacts
with the braking system is going to
allow you to cast lighter lures a
further distance and more accurately
traditionally baitcaster casters kind of
struggle at throwing lures that are
lighter than a quarter of an ounce in
weight jig head with a plastic uh
anything lighter than that and a lot of
guys would view spinning setups as being
the prime go-to for finesse fishing
applications and while it's not perfect
i will say that this does offer an
angler a little more control and a
little increased casting distance and
control over your lure if you decide to
throw an eighth ounce on a jig head or
an eighth ounce on a weighted twist lock
just a small paddle tail you're going to
have more options with this sv spool and
we're going to dive into that here as we
take off the side plate take a closer
look at the magforce braking system the
magnetic braking system on this reel and
how it works in conjunction with this sv
spool design so let's dive right in and
take a closer look at how dioa's sv
spool inside works in conjunction with
their magforce magnetic braking system
so this dial here on the side has
settings from 0 all the way to 20 and
that's going to determine how much
magnetic force is being applied to the
spool this little screw here on the
outside i'm just going to back that off
there's some guys that can do this with
their their fingernails and fingertips i
am not that savvy so let me take a
little tool and pop that off and this is
spring-loaded so this you're not going
to lose this piece it's not going to
back out
just twist the side plate down
let's wiggle that off there we go
and you get to see the inside of this
reel so let's take it piece by piece and
let's see if this makes sense
so
the concept of this sv spool design guys
is what you see here this little orange
cup
this is what daiwa calls their inductor
cup or inductor rotor and what this does
is you see it kind of moves out and in
out and in
so this is actually what is working in
conjunction with the magnetic system
here on the side plate of this reel
these rings right here
on the inside are magnets and depending
on whether like i said you're at 0 or 20
is going to determine how much magnetic
force is going to work in conjunction
with this sv spool
and what this does the concept is
when you cast and the spool is rotating
as fast as it possibly can at the top of
your cast this inductor cup is going to
shoot out okay and when it does it's
going to work in conjunction with these
magnets and depending on how you have it
set it's going to apply more or less
resistance during the cast it's not
putting resistance on the spool itself
this induct rotor is actually what is
providing the resistance on the spool
really really cool design
as you guys are going to see here in
this video there were many many many
casts i'd say let's say 9 out of 10
casts that i had that i was able to cast
as hard as i could with a couple
different lure styles i started with our
slam shady bomber as you're going to see
here on just an eighth ounce weedless
weighted hook and it's an owner twist
lock and i started by pre-setting my
tension adjuster and my cast control my
my braking system on the right on the
left-hand side of the reel and cast as
hard as i could
and i could not backlash it i mean it
did not have a professional overrun
didn't have to use my smart thumb and
slow down that spool at all it did its
job it was pretty impressive to do i
can't say that i've had that ability
with other bait casters that i've owned
fishing in freshwater scenarios so as
you can see the sv concept really does
work it's a pretty ingenious design in
terms of providing equal pressure
magnets is definitely the way to go as
opposed to a traditional centrifugal
braking system that will physically
provide resistance on the spool when it
spins this is 360 degrees of resistance
to slow down that spool while it's
spinning and at the end of the cast what
will happen is this inductor cup will
work its way back in and further away
from the brakes so it kind of adjusts
the way that this spool is spinning and
that is what ultimately prevents the
backlash here on this type of spool i
want to crank this up a notch i know
that i can cast this to tula svtw uh
without my thumb and not bird's nest but
i want to try to skip a lure if i were
to skip underneath a mangrove or a dock
i want to see how well this is going to
perform without having my thumb on the
spool so i've got a just a weedless
bomber with an owner-weighted twist lock
i'm going to skip this around a couple
times without using my thumb on the
spool to control the cast and see if we
can uh see if it's gonna hold up and not
bird's nest and that type of scenario
there's first skip
no bird's nest let's bring it back in
a second skip
good
oh
good there had a little bit of an
overrun but surprised that that one was
pretty close to me and
did not blow up into a giant bird's nest
that one for sure should have bird's
nest i'm not gonna lie
that was that was right here just just
three feet from me
okay that's that's pretty impressive i'm
not gonna lie
normally when you think about using a
baitcaster and just smacking the water
five feet in front of you you would
expect a bird's nest and so far i'm
getting pretty consistent casts on this
setting and getting i don't know that
i'd say that's 40 feet of distance
skipping a soft plastic rigged weedless
so pretty cool another cool feature on
this baitcaster is daiwa's tws system
and for those of you baitcast
enthusiasts you're probably already
familiar with this feature it's included
in about 70 percent of daiwa's
baitcasters 150 bucks and more
this tws or t-wing system as they call
it let me kind of show you guys and get
this centered
essentially what it is
is the level wine aperture that they've
redesigned and re-engineered
you see this opening here is much bigger
than what is on a traditional level wine
on a bait caster and the idea is that by
having a bigger opening when you go to
cast and line is peeling off the spool
this bigger opening is going to allow
for line to travel left and right off
the spool without as much friction and
resistance and that's going to equate to
further casting distance because the
line is not fighting itself to get out
of a smaller opening on say a
traditional baitcaster so i have a lose
speed spool tournament i had this for a
couple years just got 12 pound fluoro on
it it's my go-to finesse bass fishing
tool when i'm throwing a wacky rig but
most traditional bait casters have a
pretty small or narrow
opening in their in their level wine and
like i said when you when you're reeling
it may line the line back on smooth and
straight but when you go to cast there
are going to be times where the line is
all the way to the left or the right of
the spool and it's essentially fighting
itself to work its way out through the
smaller opening so by increasing the
area that the line can travel through
you're going to have less resistance and
therefore an increase in your casting
distance now to address a couple of cons
here with this particular tetula svtw
is that even though this magforce this
magnetic braking system matched with an
sv spool offers you a lot of control
and you know the ability to cast lighter
lures a further distance
from a casting distance standpoint this
style of braking even if you have it set
all the way to zero there's always going
to be tension applied here at the spool
so you're inherently going to have a
little bit of a reduction in casting
distance there's a number of casting
contest videos out there showing the
tetula
svtw against a shimano dc baitcaster and
a few other different models where other
reels will outperform casting distance
by let's say 10 or 15 feet to be fair
so if you're the type of person that
just
wants to go the distance and cast a big
lure across an open flat and cover a lot
of ground
this might have a limiting factor that
you guys need to keep in mind and
additionally when it comes to line
capacity so i put i was able to fit 90
yards of 30 pound braid on here you
could probably fit about 100 yards of 20
pound braid there are other 100 to 150
size
bait cast spools that will hold a lot
more line i think the coastal uh svtw
holds like 200 yards a 20 pound braid so
if you think you're going to go after
let's say a big bull redfish or
potentially a big snook and you know
it's going to dump a lot of line
line capacity is is going to be a little
bit lower on this particular tetula a
lot of other baitcasters hold between
you know 150 and 180 yards of 20 pound
braid you're only looking at about a
hundred yards with this particular model
um so the line capacity is going to be a
limiting factor as well and if any of
you out there are wondering when you
might want to fish with a bait
for inshore saltwater scenarios i can
tell you right now anybody over there in
texas any of you guys fishing the uh the
gulf coast marshes
you already know what's up when it comes
to having accurately placed casts and
having control over your casts it is
pretty hard to beat a baitcaster once
you dial it in and once you get it to
the settings that work for you as an
angler
and the same for those guys that are
fishing around structure if you're
skipping up underneath mangroves and
docks and you want to beef up that line
to 30 or maybe even 40 pound test and
you want to accurately get that lure
from a to b right where the fish is is
sitting with practice you have a lot
more control and a lot more settings
that you can tweak out here on a
baitcaster
so it definitely is a utility
reel
it has more applications for accurately
presenting lures i think in a shorter
distance than fishing out in the wide
open where you're trying to power fish i
definitely think that a baitcaster
shines in that type of setting and for
those guys that are going to be skipping
up underneath docs here in the winter
months this reel is actually going to be
luke's popping up in videos here i'm
sure in the future
great great tool i think this is a good
tool to match up with a seven foot
medium heavy or seven six medium heavy
rod and uh winching fish away from
structure this is going to be a great
tool to have in your arsenal if you want
to pick yourself up one of these tetula
svtw baycasters we have some available
on our shop page fishstrong.com guys got
to head over and check it out if you
have any questions about this baitcaster
leave a comment down below i'd love to
hear your thoughts and if you're new to
saltstrong just know that we're the best
online fishing club in america that
teaches you how to catch more redfish
sea trout snook and flounder there's
nothing else like it guys we literally
guarantee you're going to catch more
fish while saving time and money we do
this with our premium education an
exclusive
insider community and huge discounts on
all the tackle that an insure angler
needs so to learn more head over to
saltstrong.com and we will see you on
the water soon